soft engineering radio episode 128 web
application security with Bruce amps
[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet
I see radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every 10
days thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website possible
[Music]
hello everybody
welcome to se radio this is Marcus
speaking the episode today is a somewhat
special episode it's the first of four
episodes were recorded live at this
year's Opie conference and Munich
Germany it's not just a conference
recording you know it's not like on all
these other podcasts we actually did
this session as an interview or as a
kind of you know in-between between a
normal demo and an interview so this
session today is with Bruce amps and he
talks about software security and then
web application security but before we
get started I really want to thank
Francis Polish and sixth accom Francis
is the chair of LP and six datacom is
the organizer for taking the risk to
actually do this different kind of
session I think it worked quite well and
the feedback was was okay but still it
was it was a risk to do it then so thank
you very much for doing that
okay we'll have more sessions like that
coming along rig we recall it for
sessions at o P and today is the first
one as I said Bruce Sam's on software
security in the context of web
applications have fun before we get
started with topic I guess Bruce's I
think it's a good idea for you to
introduce yourself to the audience here
and the ones listening some time good
thank you
my name is Bruce Sam's I'm the guest
chef
president president the president of
Optima business information technologies
we are a company here in Munich a firm
same man from the same person company
specialized in the area of application
security and so what we work on
primarily is how do you make web
applications or middleware applications
secure we don't do very much really with
traditional security like firewalls and
and routers and all that sort of stuff
and network protocols because and this
is one of the things we're going to talk
about in this session is in fact most of
the problems most of the security
problems the vast majority of them are
really software problems they have to do
with the fact that developers didn't
know exactly what they were doing then
when they were writing the software or
that there are bugs in the software so
that's where the focus of our talk today
from the organizational standpoint I
have a demo that I would like to show
you we'd like to show you concrete
examples of some of these hacking
techniques and then after that we're
going to go over into the interview
format but first question how many of
you have seen a live hacking demo of web
applications being hacked
a couple of these have seen it okay
good then so we just start just go area
all right
I hope you have a little bit of time for
questions afterwards we'll see
I'll gossip all right so what I wanted
to show you first of all is just the
kind of things that can be done and but
when you want to hack a web app we do
this a lot because we do a lot of what
we call penetration testing which is
basically somebody hires us to attack
their web apps and then we tell them
what we found and how they can correct
the problems so what I want to do here
is to show you some of these weaknesses
some examples of problems that can come
up in web apps and then try to relate
those to the problem and the software
okay because
you know if you have a problem with SSL
for example there's nothing that you can
do about it right there's a problem in
the algorithm forget it it has nothing
to do with you but their problems we're
going to talk about here are in fact
software problems so first of all I have
a little web application that I wrote
here it's running on this powerful
server right here and we're gonna go one
time to the application I'll show you
how it works there are no problems with
the application in terms of the
specification of what it does but it's
full of holes it could be called the
Swiss cheese application so and we know
we can trust the people who wrote this
application because they have this
wonderful little gift right down here it
says there a foo bar trusted partner
like having a five-star thing on the
website right all you do is save the
gift as something else and pop it into
your own website it's absolutely
meaningless little insignia okay so
we're getting this this website offers
cars for sale at incredible discount
prices I'm all out of full quarter of
the original price unfortunately cars
are still too expensive for me umm
Lamborghinis Ferraris Aston Martin's and
so on and so forth but we can correct
that as I'll show you in a moment
so I'll make an order here
the credit card number is not checked so
don't it's not really mine
order a Porsche take two cuz they're
cheap
let them be delivered by the local boys
and there we go okay so that's how
that's how the application works from a
technical perspective it's written in
Java
although the attacks I'm going to show
you don't really have anything to do
with job you could have exactly the same
functionality and the same problems in
PHP or net or in Ruby on Rails or
whatever right away as as a sort of a
software security kind of guy when I
look at this I say oh I see two places
already where right away I would think
about attacking the system there the
first one is that in this page it says
dear Bruce thank you for your order
that's part of the reply and the reason
I think it might be bad is that it's
some of my input which is now in the
output that's not always a problem but
it happens a lot in websites that you
know you log yourself in and alpha me on
the way through the app it says dear mr.
Smith thank you for ordering whatever
right so part of the input is then in
the output the other thing which is
little suspicious to me is this little
order ID over here which looks like it
ought to be some sort of a big random
number but if you went to the website
and you ordered a lot you might find out
that there's a system to it and many
many web apps have the following problem
it's there's a back-end application and
the backend application is connected to
some sort of web front end but the
backend application may be it's an
insurance app or something has got some
sort of standard system for giving out
policy numbers or the number for
contracts it's the year the month the
day followed by an integer that is
incrementing or something like that so
it's possible to guess these things and
if the software doesn't disguise that to
the end user it's possible to attack so
anyway I'm gonna copy this thing right
here since I'm not from Libya North
Korea or Russia we can expect this will
be delivered very soon and the
application offers us another
functionality here just a little bit I
can put in my tracking number and check
the status of my order okay that's it
super unfuck super simple but let's look
and see what we could do if we wanted to
attack this application let's just go
back for example to this and take one of
these simple examples that I mentioned
to you before for example if you went to
this app when you ordered several
automobiles you would notice that
there's a system to it and you know you
might be able to put in some different
number here
and get somebody else's
order out
see who comes up this time yeah all
kinds of people have ordered cars here
um and you'd be surprised at how often
this kind of really simple problem
occurs in web applications and it's not
that it's impossible to correct in fact
actually it's pretty simple to correct
with something like a hash table and a
lookup table you know what you really
want is some sort of a standard
component for your architecture that
everybody can use that says this is what
this is the numbers that you use on the
back end and these are the numbers that
use on the front end and there's a
lookup table between the two of them to
make sure that what the end users get is
really a random number and doesn't have
to do with your internal tracking system
which might be easy to attack
so they're problems that sort of come up
because somebody wasn't thinking about
the architecture of the system there are
other problems that can come up in web
apps just because somebody didn't
configure the system right like in this
case everybody knows about directory
browsing right who knows about the right
tree browsing I hope you all raise your
hands thank God okay so we have this
directory browsing problem here but
directory browsing can actually be kind
of subtle because what happens is that
in this case I've got a combination of
directory browsing as a problem plus I
have the fact that somebody was
modifying files and left a file on the
system called dot back one of my ge'ez
peas is up there but in the form that
back right so now that I know this file
exists I can click on it and OH
because it's not a JSP it doesn't get
pushed through the compiler right so I
see the qualitex so if you are unlucky
enough to have developers that actually
comment their code it doesn't happen to
everybody but it could after you if
you're unlucky enough to have developers
to comment their code then what you find
here is all kinds of nice information in
this case about how the database table
is looked up and how the tables are
arranged and how this JSP goes about
getting information out of the database
dot dot dot now normally you know you
would say well wait a minute um why
don't we we shouldn't have comments in
our web pages anyway you all know that
hopefully no no comments and the web
pages with HTML comments it says if you
have problems with this page peace
called the system administrator Bob
Miller at Papa pop whatever number yes
but in this case it's a JSP comment
actually it should be harmless
because you should never see it
but you will see it if there's a mistake
in the system configuration right so
what I'm what I'm trying to get at is
here there are a lot of different
problems that can come up you can fix
them for example with the secure
deployment process in a secure
deployment process is one of the things
that we work on a lot secure deployment
process you could do something like for
example make a little scanner we've got
these things that we use and we use them
with our customers a lot and it scans
through all the GSP pages and it strips
all the comments out before the thing
even gets to the deployment right then
it can never happen right security okay
anyway so we have a lot of different
kinds of problems let me go back here to
another issue here on the main page here
with this check the status of your order
now how many of you have heard of SQL
injection right okay good so we're not
gonna go into all of the details about
everything that you could possibly do
with SQL injection but it's pretty clear
if you're a hacker and you look at this
if you look at this page you say to
yourself wait a minute I type in a
tracking number and then the system says
I've got the car or I've got the order
so probably there's a select in there
where the Select says show me the row
where the tracking number is equal to
whatever it is this a B X Y Z thing that
we had for it before so one thing you
can do in this kind of a situation is
to type in this kind of a thing here
which basically um is true for every row
in the table because if you have a
select statement and the where Clause of
the Select statement accepts the user
input directly without filtering it then
what you get there is just have
something like select order where order
number is equal to one two three four
five six or one is like one or one is
always one right so if we say check
status here then we get the whole table
out and
it's amazing how often this kind of
problem happens and it even happens it
happens a lot on login pages right what
happens if you put in what happens if
you put in admin as the username and
then this is the password you put in
semicolon
- -
well if there's a select clause that
says log me in if for these username
the password is that if you simply put
the semicolon and then the - - you turn
the rest of the SQL house expression
into a comment and it simply logs you in
as whatever user you add to the top you
don't have to do anything special at all
you can short-circuit the entire login
system so that happens a lot - there are
lots of different kinds of problems and
most of the time I guess what I'm really
trying to get back to here most of the
time the problem is that um we have not
thought deeply and not thought for a
long time about how to build secure
software it's not that you can't build
secure web apps is that nobody does Wow
that's not true some people do
um
happens more by accident than by
planning okay so I'm not going to show
you all too many more tricks because
this can go on forever I have dozens of
them here if you want to see more ask me
afterwards
one thing I wanted to show you here
though was also this famous trick of
cross-site scripting now um I said to
you before that I thought there might be
a problem with the web application
because it said after I ordered
something it said dear Bruce thank you
for your order right so what it did is
it took my user input and it echoed it
on an output page so what would happen
if instead of my name I typed JavaScript
in the frame well then on the page and
the confirmation page would say dear
JavaScript thank you for your order
but javascript gets executed on an HTML
page almost everywhere that it is not
everywhere everywhere but almost
everywhere so that means that if you
type in JavaScript here on the next page
the JavaScript will come out and be
executed and I don't have time at the
moment unfortunately
to go through all of the details of why
this here is so dangerous but I will new
only say this
here I'm typing in my name and I give it
as my name a bit a little bit of
JavaScript and part of the JavaScript
here is an alert box and the thing that
gets shown in the alert box is that
document.cookie a document dot cookie is
JavaScript for show me the session ID
so if your web apps do this kind of
thing and a lot of them do either by
accident or by planning
then it's possible for an attacker
through an attack that takes a little
bit more time to explain than we
unfortunately have here right at the
moment it's possible for an attacker
then to misuse this I'll only show you
briefly what kind of thing can happen
here I'll just fill out a few things
here
I say purchase
okay so what I've really done here is I
haven't really hacked myself I've looked
at my own session ID not somebody else's
but this is the basic weakness that
leads to the ability for an attacker to
look at the session IDs of unsuspecting
users normal honest users logged into
the system can be attacked and their
session IDs can be stolen using this
basic kind of a trick this is a serious
problem and the amazing thing is that
it's so insidious and and so hard to
find you when when we do penetration
tests so we do a lot of testing also for
companies that have a lot of really
really competent developers and worked
very very hard at it this problem is I
would say it shows up in 85% of the
tests that we made it's almost
everywhere why because this trick the
fact that JavaScript is executed on the
page you know you can attack you can
attack the background images in HTML
tables right and and you can attack all
kinds of things with cross-site
scripting so it's very very difficult to
defend against um and I mean one of the
things we're going to talk about in the
interview is how we'd like to get away
from a situation in which most of the
attacks are then based on having to have
the developers do a lot of work what
we'd like to do is to have some sign of
a clever system where developers can go
ahead and develop software and not spend
their whole time worrying about security
they have to know about it but they
shouldn't have to spend all day long
thinking about it because we all know
that by the time you've learned the
newest version of enterprise javabeans
plus Swing + groovy + Ruby on Rails plus
plus plus plus plus you have enough to
do alright great so that's the end of my
demonstration I hope that that made it a
little bit more plastic hood and more
concrete for you now we can go straight
to our interview ok so I guess just a
comment on that I guess one one reason
why these things are so easy is that the
architecture of some of the frameworks
and tools are simply flawed
right I mean
the fact that javascript is just text
and you can put it in there and there is
nothing going on in the background I
mean it's not not about the application
architecture but about the tool language
framework architecture isn't
have to look at my answers wait so that
was improvised I'm just going actually
you know JavaScript works is designed
javascript is doing exactly what it was
supposed to do there's nothing really
wrong with JavaScript there it's just
the way that it was used in this
application but the availability of the
JavaScript there all right you get a lot
of problems you know we you get these
security is mostly a subtle problem that
occurs somehow on the edge of what's
considered normal programming that's why
people have really not noticed it for a
long time now and one of the problems
that comes up over and over again is
when you get these complex components
that interact with each other and yeah
I'm delighted for example about the new
developments in the world wide web web 2
wonderful web 2.0 is great it's so
incredibly complicated and people are
sending messages everywhere here and
there and then everything's pluggable
and everything is an interface and
everything can be replaced at runtime
it's great for my business but it it
tends to make things more complex and
and and right where all those complex
compounds come together sometimes you
get unexpected side right so secure is a
big topic all in all and we talked
specifically today about software
security in the context of network
facing of web apps so can you outline
what software security is as opposed to
the whole field
right software security now the
important thing to remember about
software security is what what really
here but really plays a difference in in
software security is um the realization
that the problems that are facing
software today the problems that are
facing all of us with web applications
in particular are not problems that you
can solve by putting up a firewall
they're not problems that can be solved
by using SSL okay these are problems
that have really to do with the
architecture the design the
implementation and the deployment of
applications it's really something that
every software developer and every
software architect should know about at
least in in their general format um let
me let me take a second here just to
mention that because you because you
asked about it SSL why do I say that SSL
is not a help well what does SSL really
do if you have a server here and you
have a client communicating with the
server SSL make sure that nobody can
overhear the conversation
that's good that's a great idea and it
also makes sure that the client knows
he's talking to the real server right to
the right one but suppose you have a
client here and you have a firewall here
and then you have the sir sorry you have
a server here at the client the firewall
and then the client
if the ssl goes through the firewall
then no matter what the firewalls trying
to do it can't possibly look at the
information that is in the s that is in
the web requests the HTTP requests
themselves the content of the requests
that's the dangerous part what I did
right there I just type stuff into the
frame into the input fields and sent
them down
SSL wouldn't have helped at all now so
it's not something that you can just
sort of turn on a switch and it's fixed
it's a difficult problem so it also
means that it's something that
developers need to care about and not
that you know the admin guy that's right
I think one of the really important
things that you have to know is that
this is the kind of security that
affects developers it's not the kind of
security that you can really push off on
somebody else here I have a little slide
that I'm showing right now and this
slide shows some recent studies of where
software of where security
vulnerabilities come from this study was
done in United States last year by the
National Institute of Standards and
technology's that's a little bit like
the German BSI when the some physician I
didn't from on thrones tecnic and what
you can see here is that they went down
and they looked at a couple of thousand
security bugs and he said where do these
things come from
the answer is 77% of them come from
applications 0% of them come from
cryptography and these little tiny tiny
slivers up there that's things like
network stacks and protocols and all
this weird stuff where everybody thinks
the security is important actually it's
fully irrelevant what's really relevant
is the big blotches at the bottom
applications and of course application
security is not just one simple thing we
don't have a chance to talk about
everything here but at
insecurity touches areas such like the
infrastructure requirements for example
compliance to certain legal requirements
unlike Sox and the PCI DSS process
security there are all kinds of
standards that might be interesting in
that area testing and Quality Assurance
on our training
you
so we've already seen some hacks that
you've shown some problems cross-site
scripting SQL injection what are the top
three problems the top three issues well
I think the top three problems when it
when it comes to software security are
related to these general areas that I
mentioned before they are related to
issues of design and architecture
implementation deployment and also
sometimes the runtime environment itself
but probably the top three problems are
one poor input validation actually
actually there's only one problem
I was recently asked to talk to make a
top 10 list of the things that
developers have to do when they write
secure software just from the software
perspective itself and I came up with
rule 1 good input validation rule to see
rule 1
because actually if you really validate
all the input that nothing can happen no
mallet normally you really have an
application in pretty good shape if you
cover all of the inputs but the problem
is that most developers are not aware of
what is really the input to a web app
for example all of the header parts of
the HTTP request are also parts of the
input and lots of applications will read
parts of the header or will write their
own information into the header that
comes up for example when you use single
sign-on systems and those can also be
very dangerous another place is poor
configuration I showed you this thing
about the directory browsing before so
poor configuration is also problem and
the thing about poor configuration is
sometimes that software group and be the
group that does the that organizes and
runs the applications and the
application servers get at loggerheads
about this because the one says you're
responsible for the at no that one says
no you're responsible for that I say
you're both responsible so you're both
artists take a look and see that it
works that is that obeys the principle
of defense-in-depth and the last place
that I think is really a serious problem
in general is that I mean somehow either
inconsistent or or too complex
authorization most most web apps get the
login part right
because it's pretty easy if you're
working in Java for example you use Jas
and a little frame appears and you type
in username and password unless you
screwed up with the database so that you
have SQL injection or something there
then you can get somebody logged in but
the authorization parts can get really
really tricky
it's not - that's why I generally I
would have to tell you I argue for web
apps where the authorization can be
really simply explained based on URL
pads you know the more complex you try
to get with your authorization mechanism
so that you say here is a JSP now this
JSP can be called by three different
user groups sting
Jochen normal users um power users and
administrator and every time you call
that one of these different groups calls
the JSP there's a little if/else block
in the JSP that says if your
administrator show the following links
if you're a power user then do that you
know and that gets really complicated
sometimes and
although it shouldn't be too hard people
make mistakes there over and over and
over again so I would say if you set up
your web app so that either a person can
call a JSP or they cannot it's a lot
easier to defend than having them call
the JSP and then the JSP hasn't inside
of it all kinds of little if-else
switches would say if you're this then
you can see that link if you're this you
can see that link that's one of the
problems that comes up can you remove
your patch because it's crap all the
time sorry ok ok so this is obviously
very relevant for web facing
applications and obviously you've shown
many examples of web applications is it
also relevant for quote normal
applications like client-server stuff or
something yeah I mean all these things
all of these things play a role most of
our customers right now are really sort
of fixated on the idea of Web Apps but I
think if you look at if you look at the
statistics of of who's really attacking
applications and why they attack it
depends a lot on what kind of what kind
of company you work for or what you're
trying to protect really there are a lot
of inside jobs these also here I'm
showing for those of you on the podcast
I'm showing a statistic a small graph
that was also done by an American group
in cooperation with the FBI and the FBI
every year in America does a survey
where they call the Computer Crime
Survey where they ask the security
experts from different companies large
companies if they were attacked by whom
how much it costs and it's all anonymous
so that the answers we think are reflect
reality even anyway what you see there
is that 80% of the companies were
successfully attacked by unknown hackers
77 77 percent of the companies were
successfully attacked by their own
employees 40 respectively 28% were
attacked by the competition either
national competition or international
competition that size the other
companies that are working in the same
area attack them and 25% were attacked
by foreign governments
foreign governments borne gum okay just
asking foreigners you know can't blow he
can't trust him yeah so these these dang
foreigners always shooting at ya
right so there are a lot of people get
attacked by foreign governments the
thing that you can learn about this kind
of information is if you look at the
who's doing the attacking those are not
script kiddies those are people who know
where it hurts and they know how to get
the information they have time money and
resources so you know and depends on
where you're working for example in
research intensive industries it's
extremely important to protect against
internal attack right if you are in the
pharmaceutical industry or if you're in
the industry if you develop some sort of
product or you have a lot of research
and development a tremendous amount of
money goes into that and your
competitors would like to know where you
are and what new products you're working
on it's extremely important for some
other places it may be less important
but that it's absolutely true that
internal attacks should not be ignored
they get
usually
of a company says everybody that works
for us is a nice guy yeah on the other
hand if you're a company with 30,000
employees good luck with the statistics
that all of them are great
so are there any standards we can we can
apply or we can look at to try to get
software more secure yes there are some
standards but most of the most of the
people who have tried to apply some sort
of a standard to creating secure
software have failed miserably
and it's actually recent it's actually
it makes sense when you think about why
they are failing one of the reasons is
that they're trying to get a
standardized process and say okay that's
what you were gonna do right they want
to do like the rational unified process
for software they want to say this is
exactly how it has to be done and not
differently and the fact of the matter
is that software and software
development is too complex some people
develop it in-house some people send
everything out without sourcing some
people do a mixture
some people work then with new languages
and new products that say are well
suited to agile development processes
and other people are working only with
waterfall processes of me it's very
difficult to take one standardized
mythology there are a couple of
standardized processes that people have
tried to use for example clasp um
this is the common lightweight
application security process clasp was a
product of rational they tried to sort
of sell it along with the rational
unified process but nobody would buy it
because the lightweight in the name does
not reflect the actual effort required
to implement this process and now it's
an open-source thing and you can get it
and download it for free from the OWASP
website another recent attempt the
Americans have something called build
security in this sort of got started has
nothing do without BSI this this thing
got started after the September 11th
bombing attacks were that the World
Trade Center attacks the American
government realized that their software
was full of holes and they said anybody
is going to write software for the
government has to fulfill certain
baseline criteria but in this case it's
more a collection of best practices
their checklist more yeah little bit
more like a checklist
and then there are these horrible ISO
standards which are gigantic and very
difficult to handle um and they not only
cover software security but all kinds of
other things and they're very very big
big like this um I so 12207 which is
probably the closest thing that a gift
that it exists to some standard for
secure software um this thing is is only
really useful if you are EAD s or Boeing
or or something like that or Emma and
and you're creating tanks and that kind
of stuff I mean it's if you make fighter
planes then it's probably not a bad idea
but if your projects are not that big
then it's a little bit overdone so
let me get right here yeah one of the
things that I would like to talk about
is that there is we feel a way to
approach this problem of writing secure
software securing web applications in
particular um and I have a diagram here
showing various stages of a typical
development process you know you've got
an analysis phase a design phase and
implementation phase and so on and so
forth and for each of these phases what
we have done we work a lot with the
secured development lifestyle cycle what
we have done is we have identified
individual measures that you can
implement and so what we recommend and
what we do for our customers is we we
say what you have is you have a box full
of possible building blocks and these
things have to be then tailored to each
company so that they actually fit your
development process because the standard
things out of a box just don't work so
it is possible to create software it is
possible to have a secure process but
you have to know what the problems are
and you have to know what measures are
sensible to apply to them to fix them
otherwise you end up with just more
paperwork and unhappy developers above
all ok so on a bass board level you can
probably say you have to do is secure
architecture secure command secure
designs the core programming doesn't
help so can you name a couple of
concrete things maybe you know and you
know one concrete thing in in some of on
each of these steps are areas that you
can do what is secure architecture or
secure design yeah that's a good
question
what is secure architecture what is
secure design well maybe the best way to
do about to talk about this would be to
look at some of the things that you can
actually set up right there to help you
right there um we think that one of the
most important things to have is an
application security policy I'm gonna
ask the developers here everybody here
does your company have an application
security policy who has one whose
company has one
really okay that's so five people one
out of ten or something like that um has
something like this the important thing
about an application security policy is
that's it's a collection of policy
statements about what the security
requirements for applications are that
is not connected directly to software
code it's not coding conventions but
it's also not so high of the policy
level that you get ridiculous statements
like confidential data must be protected
right that's the kind of stuff that's
normally in the corporate security
policy it says that and everybody says
all my confidential data must be
protected thank you very much how do I
do that
right so the thing is you know you want
to avoid really abstract comments in the
policy don't say things like we expect
you to fulfill certain legal
requirements like socks or Basel - or
PCI DSS and it also shouldn't be in a
policy um direct usage of things like
shouldn't also be direct usage of
code examples because the code changes
too fast and then it's only good for one
particular language what you want is
some area in the middle normally what is
something sensible for that this helps a
lot with the architecture because you'd
be amazed at how many architectural
questions can be answered by exactly
these kind of policies um
what helps is to have an application
security policy and derive from that
then things like a web application
policy or a web service policy that then
go into detail about for example how to
handle soap
and if you want to work with the wheat
the ws-security standards like encrypted
messages and so on and so forth what
criteria need to be fulfilled that's a
really big step in the right direction
okay
okay so um I guess then training is the
other thing right I mean you have to
make people aware
developers people
as the training is a training is of
course extremely important I think one
of the the problems with training
generally speaking is that everybody
always nods their head and say yeah yeah
yeah we should do that right but the
fact of the matter is that um in most
companies what happens is that
sometimes a link will be provided
and then it says well that's not really
our core business and so and so forth so
take a look at this and see if you can't
figure out how all that works and you've
seen that demo from the guy Sam's
remember where he did that cross-site
scripting or the SQL injection with all
that that happen for you right
so what's sensible actually what we find
what's sensible is for is some sort of
an awareness training like maybe one
hour to three hours depending on who the
target group is where everybody can
learn and see what the problems are
normally in three hours
you can tell developers clever
developers a great deal about where the
problems lie without going into the
details of exactly how you fix it and
then eventually you can also do things
like for example set up a training class
for two or three days we do this a lot -
a three-day training class in which then
the developers sit hands-on in a lab and
learn about for example we have a little
casino a web casino that we wrote and he
can play roulette and see how dangerous
it is to play roulette it was brought
home to me last weekend when I was on
the way back from a meeting and my wife
insisted that we go to Baden Baden I
discovered I'm better at playing through
that in my little software game than I
am it really playing with that but
generally speaking anyway and he's in
roulette game in the software version
that we have then you can patch up all
the holes with all the software problems
I cross-site scripting SQL injection and
other kinds of things like the own
Volker servlet and so so two kinds of
trainings are sensible one awareness
trainings that can be done for large
group and then also in-depth training
for developers I guess it's also useful
to have some kind of you know a team
that tries to break into the software
like a you know a red team that that
plays the enemy and then tries to break
into systems you build right yeah
there's a there's a definitely a utility
there I think every every company has to
try to figure out for itself whether not
the relative costs of trying to maintain
such a red team are really sensible
in theory in theory you could say
towards the end of the development cycle
right right when you're getting to the
you get to the beta version of the
software you're ready to roll out or you
have your last things in theory you
could then take two or three of your
best developers from the project and say
okay now I guys I want you two guys to
do security testing and code review
and I would like you to show me the
project manager that in the hottest
phase of the development right before
the things about to be sent out the door
that the project manager that takes two
or three of the best guys on the team
and says okay sit over there in the
corner and do something different
forget it it will never never never
happen it's just pure theory it can
never work I've never seen it work um
and that's where either a company has to
say we're gonna make a big investment
right we're gonna have a totally
independent group you know a totally
separate entity in the company that does
nothing but QA and there's a little bit
of I wouldn't say animosity but they're
not really friends with each other the
people who do the testing are really
independent that means if if one of the
best friends of the guy on this testing
team was the lead architect yep he still
says the thing is it's got big holes in
it yeah that's not so easy to work out
sometimes in companies that's where
external companies can be helpful do you
know just out of curiosity do you know
companies like security your banks or
something who have such teams or is it
really too expensive and typically
people do it by hiring outside guys
but typically people do it by hiring
outside pica which also salts the best
friend problem which would solve the
best friend problem and which also
solves the problem of having to make
sure that those people are really
constantly learning new things right for
example my employees get about 25% of
their time for research I just say I
don't know what you're doing but but do
something useful and figure out how to
break that yeah I should I know let me
do it but you have to keep learning all
the time there and that's usually not
part of the corporate culture in larger
culture in larger corporations it's a
little bit unfair right that most of you
know the approach is to solving that
problem is basically burden on
developers I mean you would have hoped
that there would be some other way yeah
it is unfair and that's why that's why
we believe that it's important to set up
this software development lifecycle with
every company that's interested in
producing secure software so that
precisely so that the developers have
knowledge that they need but but that
nobody comes in and says hey I saw this
talk where they do a lot of hacking from
Web Apps I want you guys to really think
about that and write secure software
from now on
how and and with what time because it
requires the management has to say the
management has to say you know it's
gonna cost us ten percent more to write
the projects from now on because we need
time to do that and normally that's hard
to get when people are under pressure
there are tools that you can get to help
you with writing secure software um how
many of you know and use fine bugs or
use fine bugs okay about thirty percent
the people in the room raised their hand
fine bugs is just one of a whole class
of different kinds of applications that
you can use it will help you with
software quality in general they'll find
things like cyclical references and
loops that go off in the nowhere and all
kinds of stuff in addition to finding
security problem um it's difficult
to really do a security test with these
automated tools completely partly
because findbugs is not really or the
other things are also not optimized for
finding security problems and also
because sometimes security problems are
very subtle I don't have time
unfortunately to get into that in detail
right now if you have if you're
interested in it come and talk to me
afterwards um but the bottom line is
that most of these software tools will
also produce a certain number of false
positive right and and so and false
negatives you know so they don't find
problems that are there and they also
indicate their problems with there are
none and you need to really have a fair
amount of experience with the tools to
be able to understand what the thing is
telling you you know it's that old sorry
that a fool with a tool is still a fool
to and I can say that cuz I'm a
developer also so I not mind me I don't
mean that developers are fools I mean
it's just another thing to know and
learn there is there are tools I think
that they do for example tracking of
inputs and and you know tell you whether
they have been validated sample yeah so
does that stuff work have you have used
it yeah actually we have our own tool
that we wrote does it can I stop but we
don't sell it right it's not a product
for sale that's a research tool that we
notice and but there are tools that go
in that direction and how good they are
varies widely depending on what they're
trying to find um here I have a little
Dilbert which I'm just gonna flip
through here quickly
um Dilbert is sitting in front of his
desk and somebody comes in and says
Dilbert do you have the benchmark
results
and Dilbert typical nerd says Seuss
hardener says well do you want the ten
minute explanation of why the data are
useless or do you just want a simple
here you go
the guy says I'm in sales here you go
[Laughter]
okay so yeah it's tricky with these
tools and so on and so forth yeah so we
have Tomo two more topics one is a
horror story oh I forgot the whole thing
yeah right the whole engine also to the
the web a firewall thing first if that's
your next slide I don't yeah why don't
you do web app firewalls and then I'll
tell you a couple of horror stories
they're always amusing right okay well
you know at the beginning I said
firewalls can't protect your web
applications and that's true a classic
firewall cannot because the classic
firewall it protects networks but it
doesn't protect applications now there
are a series of new products which I'm
going to some people call them web
shields you'll find them under different
names
we call them web application firewalls
and those are special products that
understand HTTP very well
and are also capable of analyzing the
stream of data flowing to a web
application and you know for example in
the when I did cross-site scripting then
I had as one of my input parameters in
the input stream there was JavaScript
there right or you could see the tags
that the little the brackets going open
and enclosing and so and so forth
conceptually a Web Application Firewall
is a filter that looks for that kind of
problem
and you can put up web application
firewalls in front of your web
applications and what the what the
producers of web app firewalls will
promise you is you turn the switch and
no matter how crappy your software is
pardon my french english no matter how
poor your software is this thing will
protect you because it filters out all
the bad stuff
um we if you're interested in this come
and contact me later we just completed a
six month long study where I had two
guys in the company and I set them on
web application firewalls and they
looked at seven products and analyzed
what they can do and what architecture
and what the performance was and all
that kind of stuff and we want to
publish this thing pretty soon just
haven't gotten around to it because it
was just finished before Christmas time
but the bottom line is this um you can
use a web application firewall it's a
good idea but web app firewall is no
substitute for writing good software
what you can do well with a web app
firewall is what I call zero-day
patching right one of the problems that
comes up over and over again
particularly with web applications is
when we do a penetration test on a web
app and we find a critical vulnerability
then the management of the company says
to us well what should we do should we
stick our head in the sand and use the
ostrich approach should we turn off the
web app and just take it off the off the
net how do we handle this problem or
should we tell our development team to
get together in a big hurry and they'll
write a patch tonight and tomorrow it's
in first of all patching software in a
big hurry is often it very very
difficult and you make more problems
than you fix or not always but it can
happen that you also then create new
problems or that the original team that
wrote the software is not really
available anymore because the software
is already two years old and the team is
all spread out so you can't patch
sometimes really fast and you don't want
to take your important application off
the web particularly if you have to have
a big sign that says due to security
problems we had to take this off the web
right so that's that's really bad but
what you can do with a web app firewall
and this is really great though is you
can if you have practiced with the web
app firewall you know how it works then
you can set up the firewall with just
one single rule in it
so the performance is good simply put
the more rules you have the slower the
performance sometimes you get these
regular expressions I mean your eyes
will pop out of your head when you see
these red eggs you know it's like 20
lines long of regular expression good
luck right the thing is really
complicated but if you write a single
rule and you stick it in the firewall
you can put the Web Application Firewall
right in the way and block that one
problem that you know about in other
words if what you're saying is if you
know what you're looking for yeah
specifically then it's useful but not as
a general-purpose catch everything
that's my you have the same one I know
okay right that's exactly it all right
so now I've told you that I have a I
have one or two moments left for horror
stories hmm
there are a lot of them take a funny one
but everybody has to be anonymous in
these horror stories that's the
interesting thing about them good I can
tell you a horror story that has to do
with what I would call developer
craziness
one that has to do with sort of
developer ignorance and one that has to
do with the fact that there was no
quality control I'll go through them
real quickly developer craziness we had
we had a penetration test where it
turned out that the developers had
wanted to be able to operate this
program from home without having to come
in and actually do the administrative
work from within the company so they put
a little extra hidden parameter all you
had to do to the web app was add admin
equals true to the URL
and you are in administrator mode no
password no password nothing right but
but here comes the best part it was a
bunch of guys
ok sorry it girls out the other story
it's a bunch of guys right young guys
and so they were a little bit bored so
they took the background of the whole
thing and they had they had about 25
pictures of blonde women in various
poses I would say and they were loaded
up to the corporate web server and there
was a little random number generator and
every time they called up the
administrative website they got a
different one of these things as the
background with the corporate logo above
it don't do that ok that's what I call
developer craziness yeah developer
ignorant we had we had recently a pen
test where the the developers were using
cocoon nothing wrong with using cocoon
what's that
cocoon is a web framework that that
transforms XML into PDF or into input
fields sort of a and and they had they
didn't bother they didn't bother to
remove the error messages or they didn't
bother to remove the message at the
bottom of the page because when I first
called up the website I looked at it and
at the very bottom it said this page
generated in 68 milliseconds by cocoon
1.8 whatever I forget I thought Oh
cocoon doesn't that come by default with
the administration console installed
all that to do was call up then the same
URL and put in the standard path to the
administration console and I could
administer the entire Cocoon
installation j-pop out the XML files
change the change the whole thing
but isn't it either Hosting problems and
application development problem so it's
both you're right it's both but to me
it's a development problem because the
developers are the ones who would have
to say in the in the cocoon itself don't
show me those files don't show me those
messages
it would have to block that out so they
gave the hint for the follow for thee
and that was what gave me the hint that
cocoon was installed at all otherwise I
would never have known
yeah they could also have done that but
exactly there are many cases and I'm
glad that you mentioned that because in
many cases as I mentioned at the
beginning like with this a directory
browsing you know instead of having the
developers arguing with the production
group saying hey it's your fault the
other guy says no that's your
responsibility why don't you both do it
because defense-in-depth says two
hurdles are better than one
the last story I wanted a quick man
quickly mentioned here was um something
where there was high speed development
involved company went to their
contractor and said we need to have an
application that has to manage our
stocks and and equity stuff and but it
has to be written in a big hurry or what
you know some big boss said the other
company has it we have to have it too so
they hired a company the company did
rapid prototyping and the entire web
application could be we could it had no
security features built into it at all
it was possible to login to the web
pages using this SQL injection thing you
could log in his administrator and
completely manipulate the entire website
but nobody had even bothered to do any
real QA testing because they were in
such a rush that's why it has to be part
of your process because if it's not part
of the process I guarantee you the
management will ignore it right okay do
we have any questions and before you ask
them I have to run to you and give you
my mic so uh any cost anyway thank you
very much thanks for the nice discussion
sure but it's I mean we still have we
should yeah yeah Oh grab it some five
million questions questions
but it's gonna work hi so if you're
using frameworks like JSF standard
frameworks
doesn't help you doing the input
validation or for example hibernate can
you rely that it helps you preventing
SQL injection absolutely um we also
noticed that the web frame frameworks in
general are also improving a great deal
that they do a lot more for security now
than they did at the beginning like if
you look at
of struts for example had very little to
offer in the way of security where Java
server faces for example offers quite a
quite a number of um good ways to do
validation and there are also frameworks
that you can use now for example the
Apache Commons validator framework is a
very good framework which needs to be
extended but which is good basically you
mentioned hibernate for example
hibernate um normally when we find an
application that uses hibernate we can't
do any kind of injection on it
I mean it's not a guarantee that it
won't work because it's still possible
for somebody to be really boneheaded
about using hibernate and to basically
write ha QL hql and then you can do HQ l
injection on the application with the
hibernate query language that can happen
right but if you go for the typical kind
of architecture where all the calls are
parameterised and it can't happen to you
so unless you sort of have your own
clever way to use it you won't screw up
hibernate is basically great so that's a
concrete thing don't build your SQL by
assembling a string but rather use
parametrized SQL queries pre build
statements exactly more questions
any other questions
okay well perfect timing absolutely
thank you very much for doing this but
thank you also thanks for downloading
and listening to solve the engineering
radio software engineering radio is an
educational program brought to you by
hillside Europe if you want more
information about the podcast and all
the other episodes visit our website at
st - radio dot length if you want to
support us you can donate to the AC
radio team via the website or you can
advertise for su radio for example by
clicking on the Digg reddit delicious
and slash dog buttons to contact the
team please send email to team @ s e -
radio net or if it is specific to an
episode please use the comments facility
on the website so other people can react
to your comments this episode of SU
radio as well as all other episodes are
licensed under Creative Commons 2.5
licence please see the website for
details thanks to Charlie Crowell and
the pod safe music network for the music
used in the show the song is called
Vegas hard rock travel
[Music]